Cook, Alice Papers /3012
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Alice Cook Papers
1956-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cook, Alice
/3012
123.5 cubic feet
122.5 linear ft.
Papers.
Correspondence, manuscripts, publications, photograph prints, memorabilia, and daily calendars.
3071688
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 30, 2002
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 02, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Alice Hanson Cook (1903 - 1998) devoted her life to helping working people, and especially working women, on four continents. What she herself called her "patchwork career" included social work, adult education, labor organizing, a tour of foreign service at the end of World War II, twenty years teaching in Cornell's School of Industrial and Labor Relations, and authoring numerous books and articles. She was a pioneer in bringing attention to issues such as comparable worth, maternity leave, and pay equity, known for both her scholarly writings and her activism on the experiences of working women around the world.
Alice attended Northwestern University's School of Speech from 1920-1924, gaining her only formal degree. (She would later receive a number of honorary doctorates, including one from Northwestern.) While enrolled at Northwestern, Alice began her studies of both economics and social work, as well as beginning her lifelong attachment to the ideals of socialism. Early employment with the YWCA's Industrial Department in the 1920s led her to find ways to use the Y for both union support efforts and attempts to organize women workers previously ignored by unions, such as domestic servants. These early efforts with the Y led to Alice's involvement with adult labor education efforts such as the Bryn Mawr Summer School for Women Workers, Arkansas' Commonwealth College, the Southern Summer School for Workers in North Carolina, and the Hudson Shore School. They also led to her first direct employment by the union movement, as she worked for the early CIO's Textile Workers' Organizing Committee.
The 1930s and 40s also mark the beginning of Alice's interests in similar developments around the world. From 1929 to 1931, she studied in Germany under a DAAD (Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst) fellowship, beginning her long association with the German system of adult and labor education. She would return to Germany after World War II, when she became the chief of adult education in Germany's American Zone for the Education Division of the High Commission, Germany. Her travels through Germany at this time combined with her own personal experiences led her to become intrigued with questions of comparative systems of labor education. She would ultimately travel throughout both Western and Eastern Europe as well as Asia in order to carry out her research.
Alice's academic career began in 1952, when she was hired by the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y. She began as a researcher in the School's extension division, but moved into a full academic teaching position in 1955. She served as a well-respected teacher in the School up to her retirement in 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3012 AV: Alice Cook Biographical Reminiscences Audio-Visual Materials /3081: SUNY Files /4209 P: Alice H. Cook Memorial Service Photographs /4238 P: Alice H. Cook Memorial Celebration Photo Display /4270: Francine Herman collection of Alice H. Cook Memorial Celebration files /4282: ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Records /4282 AV: ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Audio-Visual Materials
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Academic Files
Sub-Series A. Committee Files (ILR & Cornell University) Sub-Series B. Departmental Files (ILR & CU) Sub-Series C. Administrative Files - Research Project Files Sub-Series D. Teaching Files
Series III: Conferences and Programs
Series IV: Professional Files
Series V: Arbitration and Mediation Files
Series VI: Subject Files
Sub-Series A. U.S. Files Sub-Series B. Japan Sub-Series C. Other Countries Sub-Series D. Comparable Worth Sub-Series E. Comparative Studies Sub-Series F. Teachers Study (UFT) Research Files Sub-Series G. Working Mothers Sub-Series H. Public Sector Sub-Series I. Local Union Governments Sub-Series J. Equal Pay
Series VII: Publications and Writings
Sub-Series A. Publications Sub-Series B. Speeches Sub-Series C. Bibliographic - Card Files (in metal boxes)
Series X: Memorabilia
Cook, Alice Hanson.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
3071688
- Series Series I: Correspondence
  - A-Ad, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence between Alice Cook and Actors' Equity Association regarding union structure; comments (handwritten & typed) to Leonard Adams about manuscripts by James Morris; job recommendations with Steven Adler, former student; and miscellaneous.
  - Af-Al, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    With ANA (American Nurses Association) regarding classification systems; requests for reports from New York City schools for AFT projects; with Dr. Tadashi Takamatsu; Tokyo, regarding rights of check off and personal; job recommendations; and miscellaneous
  - Am, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Editorial; graduate school recommendations; and miscellaneous
  - Amnesty International, 1988-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letters to various countries regarding human rights abuses
  - Anderson, Nels, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence discusses joint effort between ILR and UNESCO Institute for Social Sciences (Germany) for project on labor management in Europe; research & editorial matters; and personal.
  - Ar-Av, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Regarding reference and recommendations; with Douglas Ashford, Director Cornell University Center for International Studies regarding travel support for trip to Japan, and educating leaders for Black Communities; and other miscellaneous.
  - Babiskin, William, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes draft of personnel manual he wrote for Nippon Telegraph & Telephone Co. in Japan and recommendation for Cornell Law School
  - Bac-Bald, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    With George Baldanzi (President, United Textile Workers of America) requesting materials in the ILR School; other routine
  - Bale-Ball, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Extension correspondence with Mitzi Bales (Public Services International & former student) discusses her career with PSI and other matters; with Prof. Robert Ballon (Sophia University, Japan).
  - Bar-Bay, 1957-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    With Jack Barbash (University of Wisconsin) regarding business and personal; with Solomon Barkin (Textile Workers of America); and other routine
  - Beg-Ben, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Student recommendations; correspondence with former students; other routine
  - Ber-Bie, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Academic references; correspondence with Andrew Biemuller (AFL-CIO Department of Legislation) regarding summer internship for ILR students and other matters.
  - Bin-Bis, 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence with Dr. R. Binapfl (Germany) regarding Marshall Plan Anniversary Celebrations; with Willi Birkelbach (Germany member of German Parliament) regarding finding employment for his daughter in the US for a 6 month period and other matters.
  - Bl, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    References and correspondence with former students
  - Bo, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Routine
  - Br, 1955-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    With former students and routine
  - Bu-By, 1955-1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Employment recommendation for former student; and other routine
  - Ca, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    ILR School Administrative memos with George Calvert; with Prof. Ralph Campbell (ILR) regarding vocational educational and other routine
  - Catherwood, Martin P. (Dean), 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    Memos regarding program planning; teaching assignments; programs for visiting professors; 14 page "Administration of the School; 7 page report to Catherwood from Alice Cook on the Harvard Trade Union Program; and other routine.
  - Ce-Cl, 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    School recommendations and routine
  - Coa-Coh, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Recommendation for former students and other routine
  - Coi-Con, 1956-1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    With David L. Cole regarding Japanese unions; with P. P. deColon (Department of Labor, Puerto Rico) regarding negotiations and other matters; with former student Thomas R. Colosi regarding career matters; and other routine.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Letter from Clinton Golden (12/8/51) regarding Cook's search for employment and labor education programs; with US Department of State regarding appointment as foreign Service Officer; Correspondence with Ralph Campbell and Martin P. Catherwood regarding her appointment of position with the ILR School (1952); other correspondences (in German needs to be translated); memo from Martin P. Catherwood (4/13/56) announcing her promotion to Associate Professor; other related.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Miscellaneous
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Exchange of memos between Alice Cook and Prof. Maurice Neufeld regarding ongoing debate research in the ILR School
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Report to Dean McConnell regarding activities; 11 page "biography" (1960); and other related
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Annual Report and other administrative materials; letter from Dean McConnell regarding her promotion to full professor (1/63); and other.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Correspondence in German (to be translated) and other personal.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    Administrative memoranda regarding retirement and sabbatical.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Routine administrative; completed form for "Who's Who of American Women;" and other personal.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Approval of employment on half-time basis and retirement; correspondence with Byron Yaffe (University Ombudsman) regarding questionnaire on admission to women by the medical schools; and other routine.
  - Cook, Alice Personal, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Correspondence regarding Ombudsman as new career with US Department of HEW and James Reist, Ombudsman at Michigan State; Copies of prefaces governing use of oral history interviews; memos regarding retirement and other routine.
  - Cook, Alice Personal Ombudsman Berkeley Conference, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Correspondence and related regarding arrangements and financial reports
  - Cook, Alice Personal Ombudsman, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes last of Advisory Committee; copy of "Report to Senate Form the Ad Hoc Committee to Study Conflict Resolution," 29 page (McMaster University); congratulations regarding Alice Cook's appointment; 15 page presentation given at the Weinberg Seminar, 11/10/71 regarding the Ombudsman's Office by Byron Yaffe and other; and routine.
  - Cook, Alice Personal Sabbatics, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    7 page "letter" from Japan-a report; 14 page Report II Alice In Japan (elsewhere); 11 page biography.
  - Cook, Alice Vita (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes copies of vitae
  - Cook, Alice War Department, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Papers regarding interrogation
  - Cook-Cor, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Personal correspondence with Una Corbett; and other routine
  - Cornell Eleven, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41a)
    Miscellaneous memos and minutes
  - Cornell London Project, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Financial regarding expenditures and correspondence, mainly administrative; proposal for study of unions in local government employment in Japan, Summer 1967; and related.
  - Cou-Cro, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Recommendations; extension correspondence with Lucille Crook, former student; and routine
  - Cu, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    With Prof. Donald Cullen regarding mock bargaining and other related issues; Correspondence and recommendations for Paul Curry, former student
  - Da-De, 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Recommendations for former students and other routine
  - Di-Dor, 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Student recommendations; and other routine with former students
  - Dou-Du, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Personal and professional correspondence with Kenneth and Agnes Douty regarding mutual interests; and other routine
  - Ea-Ede, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Personal correspondence with Anne Edlemann; and other routine
  - Edw-Es, 1956-1971 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    With Einar Edwards (Agency for International Development) personal and professional; student recommendations.
  - Fal-Farly, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Routine correspondence
  - Fam-Fl, 1957-1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    With Jack Flagker regarding personal and professional, setting up labor education programs (University of Iowa); and other routine
  - Fo, 1958-1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Fr-Fu, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Includes correspondence with Ernestine Friedmann (Washington International Center); with Jesse Friedman (St. John's College); student recommendations; and other routine
  - Ga, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    With Miles Galrin (Director, labor Education Center, University of Puerto Rico); with Prof. Phillips Garmen (University of Illinois) regarding workers education in Japan and other matters; and other routine
  - Germany, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 54a)
    Correspondence regarding Germans visiting the US and Alice Cook's visit to Germany.
  - Ge-Gi, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Student recommendations; and other routine
  - Go-Golde, 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Correspondence with Clinton Golden regarding coming to Cornell as visiting Professor, encouraging him to do an oral history interview and other matters; other routine
  - Golds, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Papers and personal correspondence by Rose Goldsen (CU, Department of Sociology); other routine.
  - Goll-Gou, 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    With former students; letter to Samuel B. Gould (President, State University of New York) suggesting the establishment of Francis Perkins Fellowships; and other routine.
  - Gra, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    With Lois Gray (Extension Director, NYC) regarding administrative, extension program planning, discussion of week for a journal of Labor education and other matters; other routine.
  - Green, Archie, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Correspondence regarding participation in ILR School Dedication and Open House (5/62); visiting lecturer (folk singer and labor historian); and other related.
  - Green-Gu, 1960-1994 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Student recommendations; other routine
  - Hab-Hand, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Student recommendations; memo from Prof. Andrew Hacker (Department of Government, CU) regarding women membership in the Statler; with Eugene C. Hagbury (Ohio State University) regarding labor education programs with Marjorie Handsaker regarding asking Alice Cook for contacts and advice for their upcoming sabbatical in Japan and other related matters; other routine
  - Hann-Haw, 1962-1985 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Hayashi, Hiroko, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    (faculty member at Kyushu University) Correspondence and recommendations regarding plans for visiting US and studying at a university on a Fulbright Scholarship, personal and professional.
  - Hec-Hel, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Her-Hew, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Personal and professional with Prof. Amy Hewes (Mount Holyoke College); other routine.
  - Hi, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Includes 11 page address by George H. Hildebrandt, "The Government's Wage-Price Policy: A Long Range View." And correspondence; with Bessie Hillman (Amalgamated Clothing Workers) regarding visiting the ILR School as guest lecturer; and other routine
  - Ho, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Hu, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    With Dr. Louise Huels (West Germany) correspondence & paper regarding foreign workers in Germany; & other routine
  - I, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Itinerary for Israel trip and routine
  - Ja, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Student recommendations and other routine
  - Japan - Research, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    Includes administrative financial, correspondence regarding funding and arrangements and other related matters
  - Jensen, Vernon, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Administrative, responsibilities at ILR while serving as University Ombudsman, and other ILR matters
  - Je-Ju, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Correspondence (personal & professional) with Mildred & Newman Jeffrey; personal & professional with Brownie Lee Jones; and other routine
  - Kac-Kam, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Correspondence regarding schedule of Hiroko Kageyama of Japan studying employment opportunities for women
  - Kan-Kar, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Recommendations for students; personal & professional correspondence with Chieko Kanno of Keio University, Japan; and other routine
  - Kau-Kan, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    With Prof. Jacob J. Kaufman (Pennsylvania State University) regarding arrangements for class lectures at CU and other personal & professional matters; with Hisashi Kawado, Keio University (Japan) regarding mutual interests and upcoming visit to the US.
  - Ke-Kl, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    Student recommendations & correspondence; & other routine
  - Knapp, Betsy, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    Correspondence and information regarding the Government In Action Project (Syracuse, NY).
  - Kni-Kor, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    Extensive correspondence with Gerd Korman (in Israel) about the Straight takeover at Cornell and the situation at Cornell in general and other matters
  - Koren, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 80a)
    Correspondence regarding her travels and with acquaintances in Korea
  - Kos-Kra, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    Extensive correspondence with Abe Kramer (Foreign Service) regarding mutual interests and friends and the field of labor relations; and other routine
  - Kro-Ku, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    Student recommendations; and other related
  - Lab-Lal, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    With Betty Lall (NYSSILR-NYC) regarding UNIM-University Urban Affairs Program; and other routine
  - Lam-Lan, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence with Prof. Henry Landsberger (University of North Carolina) regarding editorial, personal and other matters of mutual interest, includes 28 page manuscript by Landsberger entitled "On Being 'Academic' South of the Border;" and other routine
  - Lap-Leven, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Recommendations; and other routine
  - Lever-Levine, R. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with former students, Robert Levine and Edward Levine and others; with E.J. Lever regarding the library obtaining the papers of Clinton S. Golden and personal.
  - Levine, S.-Liv, 1957-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Professional and personal correspondence with Prof. Solomon Levine (University of Illinois); correspondence with David Lipsky (Dean) regarding a conference honoring Alice Cook's (and others) retirement, her work abroad in various countries; with David Livingston (District #65, RWDSU); and other routine.
  - Loh-Lu, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Personal with Val Lorwin; student recommendations; Prof. Anthony Luchek (University of Wisconsin) regarding workers education and other matters; and other routine
  - Ma, 1955-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Recommendations; and routine
  - Mc, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Recommendations for students; and other routine
  - McConnell, John W. (Dean, NYSSILR; President, University of New Hampshire), 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
    Correspondence regarding employment for students in labor unions; suggestions for speakers for classes, etc.; request for sabbatic leave to write a book on union government; participation in School Summer with steelworkers; administrative memos; and other routine.
  - McKersie, Robert B. (dean, NYSSILR), 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Administrative and other routine matters
  - Me-Mesk, 1954-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Extensive correspondence with Charles L. Medd (US Foreign Service in Japan) regarding mutual interests and mutual friends; and other routine
  - Mess-Mey, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mia-Mil, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    With Curtis Mial (Executive Director NYS Citizens; Council Inc.) regarding projects and activities Alice Cook on Advisory Committee; and other routine.
  - Min-Mold, 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Student recommendation and correspondence regarding careers with Steve Moldof; correspondence with Yoshihiro Mizuno regarding his visit and study on the industrial relations system in the shipbuilding industry between the US and Japan; other routine.
  - Moli-Mon, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Moore, David (Dean, NYSSILR), 1963-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    Memos regarding stereotype of the ILR School; teaching load; public order in the colleges; few issues of "A View for Here" memo form reports from Dean Moore; administrative matters; Frances Perkins Fellowship; Alice Cook's committee post; and other routine.
  - Mor-Morris, 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Student recommendations; extensive correspondence with Prof. James Morris; articles regarding plagiarism, workers education; sabbatic project in Chile, editorials, tenure status, and other matters; and other routine.
  - Morrison-Mos, 1954-1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Recommendations and routine
  - Mot-Muel, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Correspondence as member of Ad Hoc Committee to review qualifications of faculty applicant in College of Human Ecology' other routine.
  - Muen-Mus, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Na, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Letter from Elma Greenwood, National Committee of Churches regarding attitude of church toward organized labor; other routine
  - Ne-No, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Memos with Maurice Neufeld (ILR) regarding course offerings 11 page paper by Neufeld, "Grass-Roots Founders and Grass Roots Prodders: The Sources of Venture and renewal for Democratic Education"; and other school related matters; and other routine
  - O-Om, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Extensive correspondence with Prof. Philip Sesun Oh (Sanquk College, Seoul, Korea) who was a former student regarding personal and professional; recommendations; other routine
  - Or-Ox, 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Correspondence with Oscar Ornati (New School for Social Research) regarding personal and professional; with Prof. Charles Orr (Roosevelt University) regarding workers education in the Far East and other related matters; other routine
  - PA, 1959-1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    With Irmagard B. Parsons, NYS Joint Legislative Committee on State's Commerce, Economic Development regarding recommendations for new programs, new laws on changes to ensure equal opportunity for women; other related.
  - Pem-Per, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)